총집편 대사 번역 및 에피소드 대사 수정: Subdiver
에피소드 및 주제곡 원 번역: 하늘별 (clickally)
Translation and edits by Subdivers
Episode dialogues/songs taken from C-M/PDSG/Silver Castle
엑스카이저!
Exkaiser!
이 신비롭고 끝없이 넓은 우주 속에서
In this miraculous and endless Space,
지구는 하나의 조그마한 행성에 불과하다.
the Earth is nothing more than a small planet.
인류가 아직 모르는 선과 악의 전투가 이 크나큰 우주에서 조용히 일어나고 있다.
There is a fight between good and evil that humans do not know yet going on there, silently.
큰일이군! 놈들이 이 행성으로 도망쳐 들어갔구나!
Oh no! Those bastards are taking refuge in this planet!
이쪽은 우주 경찰 엑스카이저!
This is Exkaiser of the cosmic police!
가이스터가 지구에 숨어들었다!
The Geisters have taken refuge in the Earth.
시급히 지원을 요청한다!
Requesting backup!
엑스카이저에 대해서라면 무엇이라도 알게 되는 슈퍼 비디오!
On this super video, you'll get to know anything about Exkaiser!
싸워라! 엑스카이저
Fight! Exkaiser
지금 시작해!
Starting now!
용자 엑스카이저
Yuusha Exkaiser
푸르게 빛나는 몇천만 개의
Sparkling blue and more than millions
사랑의 조각이 흩어져 있어
The shards of love are scattered
이 지구 안에 휘몰아치는
Storms are swepting over the Earth
폭풍으로 달려가는
You decided to face the storms
너를 믿으니까
And because I believe in you
아무것도 두렵지 않아
There is nothing more to fear
GO WITH ME 엑스카이저
Go with me, Exkaiser
용기와 우정
With courage and friendship
힘을 합치는 그 순간 GATHER WAY
As soon as we join our strength, GATHER WAY
GO WITH ME 엑스카이저
Go with me, Exkaiser
잊고 있었던
Never forget again
뜨겁게 불타는 소중한 PASSIONATE 내 가슴에
The fiery burning and precious passion in my heart
-코우타.
-왜, 엑스카이저?
-Kouta.
-What is it, Exkaiser?
내가 처음 네 집에 들렀을 때를 기억하고 있니?
Do you remember when I first visited your house?
뭐야?
What was that?
응, 별이 반짝이는 추운 밤이었어.
Yes, it was a cold night with a sky full of bright stars.
큰일이야! 누나!
Fuuko! Did you see that!?
마리오, 뭔가 있으면 알려 줘. 사진 찍고 바로 돌아갈 테니까.
Mario, tell me as soon as you see something. I'll go back right after taking pictures.
어라? 아무것도 없네...
Huh, nothing's here?
이상하네...
That's weird...
뭐, 뭐야, 마리오?
W- what is it, Mario?
뭐야, 아무것도 없잖아.
What was that about? There's nothing here!
역시 꿈이었나...
Maybe it really was just a dream...
아, 맞다! 오줌! 싸겠어!
Argh, I forgot! Pee! I have to go to pee!
마리오, 어서 와, 못 참겠어!
Come on, Mario! I can't hold it any longer!
우리 집 자동차에 외계인 엑스카이저가 들어올 거라고는 생각도 못 했어!
I never thought an alien like you, Exkaiser, would come into our car!
몰래 자동차를 개조한 것은 지금이라도 미안할 따름이야.
I cannot stop apologizing for borrowing your car without permission.
공룡 박물관에서 가이스터한테 쫒겼을 때도 놀랐어!
I was also shocked when a Geister decided to chase me in the dinosaur museum!
위험해!
Watch out!
뭐, 뭐야!?
W- what is that!?
코토미, 서둘러!
Kotomi, hurry up!
살려줘!
Help me!
왜, 왜 날 쫒아오는 거야!?
W- why is that chasing me!?
나 뭐 나쁜 짓이라도 한 거야!?
D- did I do anything bad!?
헤헤. 야, 꼬맹아.
Heh. Hey, kiddo.
마, 말했어!
I- it talked!
그 보물을 넘겨라.
Hand over that treasure.
보물? 이 카메라 말이야?
Treasure? Do you mean this camera?
아, 안 돼! 이 카메라는 할아버지가 남겨주신 소중한 유산이야!
I- I can't do that! This camera is the memento from my grandpa!
우리 차가...
Our car...
아야...  뭐, 뭐냐, 너는!
Ouch... W- who are you!?
가이스터 악당놈! 이 지구에서 악행을 저지르는 것은 이 내가 용서할 수 없다!
Geister scoundrels! I will not let you do evil deeds on this planet!
우리 차가 말했어!
Our car have just talked!
그 목소리... 너... 네놈은!
That voice... you... you must be that...!
체인지! 엑스카이저!
Change,  Exkaiser!
로, 로봇이 됐어...
I- it became a robot...
네, 네이놈! 여기까지 쫒아오기냐!
Y- you bastard! You followed us to here!?
젠장, 이렇게 되었으니...
Damn. Well, then...
체인지! 혼 가이스터!
Change,  Horn Geist!
어, 어디서 감히 그런 짓을!
N- now you've done it...
시건방진!
How impudent!
제트 부메랑!
Jet Boomerang!
해냈어!
He did it!
드릴 맥스, 들리나?
Drill Max, can you hear me?
코우타가 우릴 비밀로 해 주어서 다행이야.
You really helped me by keeping me a secret.
여긴 드릴 맥스! 잘 들립니다, 무슨 일이 있는 겁니까?
This is Drill Max! What's up? Is there anything for me to do?
엑스카이저에 대한 비밀이 자꾸 쌓여가기만 해서 참!
I don't mind if it's only you, but the secrets gets more and more! It was confusing!
도처에서 전기를 도난당하고 있다. 곧바로 송전선을 조사해 주길 바란다.
There's a report that electricity is being stolen in various areas. Please investigate the power plants.
-내 동료 말이니?
-응.
-Is it about my comrades?
-Yeah.
알았습니다! 즉시 조사하겠습니다!
Roger! I'll report back shortly.
지금의 드릴 맥스 말고도 블루 레이커나 그린 레이커 밖에도 친구가 있어?
Are there more friends else than that Drill Max just now, Blue Raker, or Green Raker?
그래. 외에도 대시 맥스나 스카이 맥스가 있어. 모두 모여서 우주 경찰 카이저스야.
Yeah. We have Dash Max and Sky Max, too. We are Kaisers, the cosmic police altogether.
-그렇게나 있었구나!
-멍!
-There are so many of you!
-bark!
네게 이걸 줄게.
I want you to carry this.
-뭐야, 이거?
-카이저 브레이스. 무전기야.
-What is this?
-Kaiser Brace. It's a walkie-talkie.
그게 있으면 원할 때 나와 교신할 수 있어.
With that, you can communicate with me whenever  you want..
그렇구나.
I see.
-가자, 아우여!
-좋았어!
-Let's do it, brother!
-Right!
체인지! 블루 레이커!
Change,  Blue Raker!
체인지! 그린 레이커!
Change,  Green Raker!
레이커 브라더스!
Raker Brothers!
바인드 크래시!
Bind Crash!
체인지! 대시 맥스!
Change,  Dash Max!
체인지! 드릴 맥스!
Change,  Drill Max!
체인지! 스카이 맥스!
Change,  Sky Max!
맥스 팀 등장!
Max Team's here!
시꺼! 해치워라!
Shaddup! Deal with them!
-오오!
-해냈어!
-Wow!
-They did it!
카이저스가 모두 모이면 무서운 건 없겠네.
There's nothing to fear when all the Kaisers are together!
보물.
Treasure.
꼭 그렇지만도 않아.
That's not entirely true.
다이노가이스트 님, 전원 모였습니다.
Lord Dino Geist, everybody is here.
가이스터의 보스 다이노가이스트는 참으로 만만찮은 녀석이야.
Geister's boss, Dino Geist, isn't to be looked down upon.
니들이 꽁지 빼서 실패했잖아!
We failed because you guys ran away!
니놈이 시시한 작전이나 세우니까 그러잖아.
It's all because of your dumb strategies.
-그래, 그래! 프테라 잘못이야!
-뭐야?
-Right, right! It's all Ptera's fault!
-What did you say?
용서해 주십시오!
Please forgive us!
너희들은 어디까지 가이스터의 이름에 먹칠할 생각이냐.
Is there no limits to you when you're bring disgrace on Geisters?
다이노가이스트 님은 네놈들의 무능함에 화가 나셨다! 조금은 머리를 써!
Lord Dino Geist is angry at your incompetency! Try using your brains!
저, 정말 죄송합니다.
W- we are ashamed.
실패는 용서할 수 없다!
Failures will not be forgiven!
예!
Understood!
체인지! 프테라 가이스트!
Change,  Ptera Geist!
체인지! 아머 가이스트!
Change,  Armor Geist!
체인지! 썬더 가이스트!
Change,  Thunder Geist!
그린 레이커, 녀석들을 꼼짝 못하게 하자!
Green Raker, let's bind them!
알았어, 형!
Right, bro!
폼 업!
Form Up!
좌우합체! 울트라 레이커!
Left&Right Fusion, Ultra Raker!
맥스 팀! 폼 업!
Max Team! Form Up!
삼체합체! 갓 맥스!
Triple Fusion, God Max!
킹 로더!
King Loader!
거대합체! 킹 엑스카이저!
Giant Fusion, King Exkaiser!
해치워라!
Get him!
카이저 블래스터!
Kaiser Blaster!
울트라 더블 체인 크래셔!
Ultra Double Chain Crasher!
갓 소닉 버스터!
God Sonic Buster!
카이저 소드!
Kaiser Sword!
썬더 크래시!
Thunder Crash!
가이스터 넷도 합체했던 적이 있어.
Those four Geisters have combined once, too.
에이, 어쩔 생각이냐!
Hey, what are you up to!?
합체해도 별로 강해지진 않았지만 말이야.
They didn't become much stronger after they did, though.
사장군 합체! 매드 가이스터!
Quad General Fusion, Mad Geister!
오오, 뭔가 커진 것 같아.
Hey, it's like we've become big!
같은 게 아니라 커진 것이다!
It's not like we've become big; we became big!
힘도 네 배가 되었다는 것이로군. 이거 좋괜찮구먼! 가자, 제군들!
That would mean we have quad the strength. That's great! Let's go, people!
어, 왜 안 움직이지?
Hey, why can't I move?
아니, 내가 어깨에 붙어 있잖아! 야, 프테라, 어떻게 된 거야!?
Hey, I'm stuck on your shoulder! Ptera, what's wrong with you!?
작전은 내가 짜잖아! 내가 머리에 붙는 게 당연하다!
I make the plans! It's obvious that I assume the head!
-뭐야!?
-이야압!
-What!?
-Charge!
아, 써, 썬더, 서두르지 마! 내 작전대로 움직여!
Uh, T- Thunder, don't rush! Follow my plans!
흥! 여기까지 왔으니 작전은 더 이상 알 게 뭐냐! 가라, 가, 썬더!
Hmph! Now that we're here, there's no need for that plan nonsense! Go, go, Thunder!
좋아, 나도!
Well then, me too!
아, 부딪힌다!
We're crashing!
가이스터들의 사고방식은 이해하지 못하겠어.
I sure can't understand Geisters' way of thinking.
저런!
Damn!
그렇구나. 그럼, 엑스카이저, 지구에 대해선 좀 알게 됐어?
I see... Then, Exkaiser, do you think you've finally understood about humans in Earth?
팔로 버티고 일어나, 아머!
Use your arms to stand up, Armor!
썬더, 다리 치워!
Thunder, move your legs!
서둘러!
Hurry up!
그래, 꽤나 말이야.
Yes, pretty much..
예를 들자면, 코우타 주변에서 제일 강한 사람은 사실은 어머니라는 것.
For example, the strongest person around you is actually your mother.
뭐라고? 음, 어.
What? Um, yeah.
-엄마!
-어머님!
-Mom!
-Ms. Hoshikawa!
-살려 주세요!
-이제 틀렸어!
-Help me!
-We're doomed!
괜찮아요. 정의의 편이 저희를 내버려두거나 하진 않을 거에요!
Don't worry. A friend of justice won't abandon us!
코우타!
Kouta!
에잇! 엄마!
Here goes nothing! Mom!
코우타!
Kouta!
음? 시끄럽구만. 돌아가라!
Hm? How noisy. Go back!
이 괴물 놈! 우리 아들한테 무슨 짓이야!
You monster! What are you doing to my child!?
저런!
Dammit!
-코우타!
-엄마!
-Kouta!
-Mom!
금연!
No Smoking
그리고 코우타 집에서 제일 눈치보고 사는 게 아버님이지.
And the one with the least liberty in your home must be your father.
음, 그래?
Well, that might be true.
봐 줘라. 정이 있잖냐.
Please pretend I didn't do that. We've been knowing each other too long.
고기 붙어있는 뼈다귀 사줄 테니까, 응? 알았지?
I'll buy you a bone with meat on it! Is that good enough for you?
그럼 염원하던 한 개비를...
At last, it's time for one...
아빠!
Dad!
아, 아니, 그게...
Well, you know, that...
-아빠, 여기 와요!
-아야야야, 당기지 마!
-Dad, come with us!
-O- ow! Don't pull!
아, 왜 맨날 이렇게 되는 걸까...
Why does this always happen to me?
상상력이 제일 풍부한 사람은 누나 후우코겠지?
The one with the richest imagination must be Fuuko, I think.
그러니까 맨날 남자친구도 안 생기지.
That's why I never get a boyfriend...
상상력이야?
Imagination, huh...
애인 있으면 좋겠다...
I want a lover...
-다친 데는 없는 것 같구나.
-어? 저, 저기, 잠깐만요!
-It seems that you aren't hurt.
-Huhh? H- hey, wait!
정말... 정말 근사한 목소리야...
Truly... What a lovely voice...
다친 데는 없었습니까, 아가씨?
Are you alright, miss?
칠석날 전 밤에 만나게 될 줄이야... 참으로 운명적이야!
I never thought this would happen on the night before the day of Vega... What a fate!
분명 이건 일생에 한 번 있을까 말까 한 사랑일 거야.
This must be the love that only happens once at most in the whole life.
토쿠다 씨는 촐랑이여도 용감한 사람이야.
Mr. Tokuda is a scatterbrain, but he's still a brave person.
그럴 수도 있겠네.
That's... probably the case.
좋아! 이렇게 된 이상 토쿠다 오사무, 일본 사내의 이름을 걸고 안테나를 수리해 보이겠다!
Well then! I, Tokuda Osamu, will repair the antenna, in the name of Japanese man!
네이놈!
You bastard!
좋아, 여기구나. 정말 끔찍하군.
So this must be it. How awful...
토쿠다 씨, 같은 색의 코드를 이어 주세요.
Mr. Tokuda, please connect the cables in the same colors.
알았어요. 같은 색 코드를 이으면 되는 거죠?
I got it. I'll connect the cables in the same colors!
스위퍼가 안 움직이면, 달은, 일본은 대체 어떻게 되나?
I must get the sweeper to work, or neither the Moon or Japan won't be anymore!
편집장, 토쿠다가 사내가 됩니다! 음!
Chief editor! Tokuda will become a man!
에이, 시건방진.
How impudent!
그 정도냐, 다이노가이스트!
Is that all you have, Dino Geist!?
좋아! 됐다!
There! It's done!
전용 안테나가 빛났어!
The antenna just shined!
-움직이기 시작했어!
-늦지 않겠지!?
-It started to move!
-I hope it isn't too late!
발사!
Fire!
뭐야!?
What the-!?
생각해 보면 알 수 없는 일 천지야.
Looking back, there is so many stuff that I don't get it.
드래곤 제트는 지금까지 어디에 있던 거야?
Where did you keep Dragon Jet all this time?
아! 킹 로더가 당하겠어!
Look! King Loader won't take it for long!
그건 비밀이야.
That's a secret.
합체할 수 없다면 이 몸에게 상대할 수 있을 리가 없겠지!
Being unable to combine, you won't be standing me anymore!
가이스터 악당 놈들! 내 합체를 저지시켰다고 이길 거라고 생각하면 크나큰 오산이다!
You villainous Geisters! If you think interrupting my combination will get you anywhere, you are gravely mistaken!
흥.
Hmph.
드래곤 제트!
Dragon Jet!
쳇. 쓸모없는 놈이 또 있었군.
Tch. Another useless one to deal with.
폼 업!
Form Up!
거대합체! 드래곤 카이저!
Giant Fusion, Dragon Kaiser!
뭐야?
What!?
아, 엑스카이저가 또 다른 로봇이 됐어!
Hey, Exkaiser became another different robot!
드래곤 앵커!
Dragon Anchor!
이 무슨!
No way!
-틀렸어!
-달아나!
-서둘러!
-This isn't good!
-Run!
-Hurry!
드래곤 아처리!
Dragon Archery!
썬더 애로!
Thunder Arrow!
있잖아, 트레이더에 대해서 알려줄래?
Hey, can you tell me about Trader?
놈은 악당을 상대하는 우주 상인이야. 그런 놈이 있으니까 악이 따라오는 거야.
He's a space merchant doing business with villains. People like him is the reason why evil won't stop in this world.
체인지! 트레이더 ...왔수!
Change,  Trader ...at your service!
잘도 기억해냈구먼! 자, 그럼.
You do remember me! Well then.
아빠 카메라!
Dad's camera!
어디, 보자. 이건 이렇고, 저건 저렇고...
Let me see, then. This is good, that's good, ...
5억이다!
500 millions!
으아악! 도무지 다이노가이스트 씨는 못 당하겠다니까! 좋수! 5억으로 합시데이!
Oh my! I really am not a match for you, Mr. Dino Geist! Well then, it's 500 millions then!
물건은 먼저 가져가도 되겠수?
May I take the goods first?
그러던가.
Whatever.
소유자 이송 허가.
The owner agreed to the transportation.
체인지! 다이노가이스트!
Change,  Dino Geist!
이런!
Oh no!
나스카에서 일어난 일도 불가사의했어.
What happened at Nazca was mysterious, too.
피해 봐라! 내 필살의 검을!
Try to avoid my deadly swords, if you can!
선조가 우리를 위해 남겨둔 힘이야.
It was the power the our ancestors left for us.
다크 썬더 스톰!
Dark Thunder Storm!
그 때 나는 내게 무슨 일이 일어났는지 이해하지 못했었어.
Back then, I couldn't understand what happened to me as well.
드래곤 카이저!
Dragon Kaiser!
우주 해적 가이스터에게 맞선 죄값을 치러라!
Suffer the retribution of going against the space pirates Geisters!
이렇게 당할 수는 없다! 이 지구를, 코우타와 모두를 가이스터에게서 지키지 않으면...
I can't be defeated here! I must protect this Earth... and protect Kouta and the others from Geisters!
그 목 가져가겠다!
Off with your head!
음? 이건?
Huh? What's that?
뭐, 뭐지, 이 빛은?
W- what's with this light?
몸 속으로 에너지가 흘러들어오고 있다!
I can feel the energy flowing into my body.
킹 로더!
King Loader!
폼 업!
Form Up!
초거대합체! 그레이트 엑스카이저!
Super Giant Fusion, Great Exkaiser!
뭐야!? 다이노 실드!
How dare you! Dino Shield!
후후후, 보았느냐! 뭣이!?
Hmph, you couldn't have withstood that. What!?
이건 어떠냐!
How's this!?
그레이트 플레임!
Great Flame!
이 대체 무슨 힘이냐.
What kind of power is that?
카이저 소드!
Kaiser Sword!
썬더 크래시!
Thunder Crash!
젠장, 어디 두고 보자!
You haven't seen the last of me!
엑스카이저!
Exkaiser!
대단해! 다이노가이스트가 놀라서 달아났어!
That was awesome! Dino Geist got frightened and ran away!
나도 드디어 깨달았어.
I finally understood, too.
응. 새 힘이란 건 이걸 말했구나.
Yes. That new power must be meaning this.
그래.
Yes, you're right.
그 힘이 있으면 분명 다이노가이스트도 쓰러뜨릴 수 있을 거야!
With that power, you'll manage to take down Dino Geist for sure!
그래. 꼭 쓰러뜨려 보일게!
Agreed. I'll take him down no matter what!
부탁이야, 엑스카이저!
Please do, Exkaiser!
아득한 바람이 꿈을 가져와
Faraway wind carries your dream
설레이는 일에서 무엇을 찾아낼까
What could you discover from this excited feeling
강하고 빠르게 부풀어 오르는 꿈에
Dreams get bigger strongly and fast
자신다운 모습을 잊지 말고
Don't forget to be who you are
정열적인 마음 꼭 껴안고
Embrace your enthusiastic heart
그 길을 걸어가 보는 거야
And try walking that path
엑스카이저!
Exkaiser!